<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tr:pub-pt xmlns:form="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/form"
           xmlns:ls="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/ls"
           xmlns:tr="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/tr"
           xmlns:lnci="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/common/lnci"
           xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
           xmlns:se="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/se"
           xmlns:pnfo="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/pnfo"
           xmlns:in="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/in"
           xmlns:header="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/header"
           xmlns:lnb-leg="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/lnb-leg"
           xmlns:fm="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fm"
           xmlns:di="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/di"
           xmlns:su="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/su"
           xmlns:pu="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/pu"
           xmlns:core="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/core"
           xmlns:em="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/em"
           xmlns:fn="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/fn"
           xmlns:glph="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/glph"
           xmlns:nl="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/nl"
           xmlns:ps="http://www.lexisnexis.com/namespace/sslrp/ps"
           lni="4T0V-VG10-R03M-12R2-00004-00"
           pub-acronym="TCL"
           volnum="Binder_01/Division_1">
   <core:no-title/>
   <tr:ch>
      <core:title>Misrepresentation</core:title>
      <core:toc>
         <core:title>Contents</core:title>
         <core:comment type="commentary">
            <core:para>All references are to paragraph numbers</core:para>
         </core:comment>
         <core:toc-entry>
            <core:entry-title>Misrepresentation Act 1967 <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                  <lnci:content>[229]</lnci:content>
               </lnci:cite>
            </core:entry-title>
         </core:toc-entry>
         <core:toc-entry>
            <core:entry-title>Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                  <lnci:content>[243A]</lnci:content>
               </lnci:cite>
            </core:entry-title>
         </core:toc-entry>
      </core:toc>
      <lnb-leg:legislation>
         <lnb-leg:act acronym="MA 1967">
            <header:metadata type="legislation">
               <header:metadata-item name="normcite" value="1967_7a"/>
            </header:metadata>
            <lnb-leg:prelims>
               <lnb-leg:officialname>
                  <core:title>Misrepresentation Act 1967</core:title>
               </lnb-leg:officialname>
               <lnb-leg:officialnum>Chapter 7</lnb-leg:officialnum>
               <core:comment type="commentary">
                  <core:generic-hd level="2">Preliminary notes</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Scope of the Act</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para edpnum-start="229">The Act is concerned with the remedies available for ‘innocent’ misrepresentation, that is non-fraudulent misrepresentation. Section 1 removes two bars to rescission of contracts for non-fraudulent misrepresentations. Section 2(1) provides a remedy in damage against a person who, by a misrepresentation, induces another to enter into a contract with him, unless the representor can prove that he had reasonable ground to believe and did believe that the representation was true. Section 2(2) gives the court a discretion to award damages in lieu of rescission for non-fraudulent misrepresentation. Section 2(3) provides that damages under sub-s (2) may be awarded in addition to damages under s 2(1) and arranges for the former damages to be taken into account in assessing the latter. Section 2(4) prevents a person from claiming damages under s 2 where there is a right of redress under the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (SI 2008/1277), Pt 4A, see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                        <lnci:content>1A[54A]</lnci:content>
                     </lnci:cite> ff. Section 3 prevents the exclusion or restriction of liability or remedies for misrepresentation unless the term satisfies a test of reasonableness for contracts that do not fall under the Consumer Rights Act 2015, Pt 2, see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                        <lnci:content>[6061]</lnci:content>
                     </lnci:cite> ff. Section 4 has been repealed. Section 5 contains savings for past transactions.</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Enforcement orders</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>This Act is included amongst those listed in the Enterprise Act 2002 (Part 8 Domestic Infringements) Order 2003 (SI 2003/1593), see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                        <lnci:content>[188]</lnci:content>
                     </lnci:cite> as acts or omissions amounting to domestic infringements under the Enterprise Act 2002, s 211(2), see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                        <lnci:content>[64]</lnci:content>
                     </lnci:cite>. This means that, in addition to any civil proceedings brought under the Act itself, the CMA and other designated enforcers may also apply for enforcement orders under Pt 8 of the Enterprise Act 2002. For full discussion of this see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                        <lnci:content>[63]</lnci:content>
                     </lnci:cite>ff.</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Scotland</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act does not extend to Scotland (s 6(3)).</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Northern Ireland</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act does not extend to Northern Ireland (s 6(4)).</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Citation</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act may be cited as the Misrepresentation Act 1967 (s 6(1)).</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Amendment</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act has been amended by the Sale of Goods Act 1979; the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977; the Consumer Protection (Amendment) Regulations 2014 (SI 2014/870); and the Consumer Rights Act 2015. All amendments have been incorporated where applicable.</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Commencement</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act came into force on 22 April 1967 (s 6(2)).</core:para>
               </core:comment>
               <lnb-leg:longtitle>An Act to amend the law relating to innocent misrepresentations and to amend Sections 11 and 35 of the Sale of Goods Act 1893.</lnb-leg:longtitle>
            </lnb-leg:prelims>
            <lnb-leg:main>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="229A">
                  <core:desig value="1">1</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Removal of certain bars to rescission for innocent misrepresentation</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>Where a person has entered into a contract after a misrepresentation has been made to him, and–</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para2>
                     <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>the misrepresentation has become a term of the contract; or</lnb-leg:para2>
                  <lnb-leg:para2>
                     <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the contract has been performed;</lnb-leg:para2>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>or both, then, if otherwise he would be entitled to rescind the contract without alleging fraud, he shall be so entitled, subject to the provision of this Act, notwithstanding the matters mentioned in paragraphs (<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>) and (<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>) of this section.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section removes two bars to rescinding a contract induced by a non-fraudulent misrepresentation. Rescission involves setting aside the contract so as to restore, so far as possible, the state existing before the contract was made.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The Act provides no definition of ‘misrepresentation’. It has been held in cases prior to the Act that mere puffs are not covered by the term and that representations as to the future or as to law are also excluded.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Section 1 requires the misrepresentation to have been ‘made’ and thus cases of non-disclosure will not be covered, though partial non-disclosure may be sufficient.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">‘If otherwise he would be entitled to rescind the contract without alleging fraud’</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This requires that there be no other bar to rescission operating, for example, affirmation or lapse of time. The bar operating where a contract has been performed, now removed by s 1(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>), never applied to cases involving fraud; <core:emph typestyle="it">see</core:emph> 
                        <core:emph typestyle="it">Gillett v Peppercorne</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1840) 3 Beav 78, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>; <core:emph typestyle="it">Spence v Crawford</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1939] 3 All ER 271, HL</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>;</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="6">SECTION 1(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>Prior to the Act it was suggested that, if the misrepresentation had become a term of the contract, the law relating to misrepresentation was not relevant, and the case would be decided on the basis of a breach of a contractual term alone; <core:emph typestyle="it">see</core:emph> 
                        <core:emph typestyle="it">Pennsylvania Shipping Co v Ce Nationale de Navigation</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1936] 2 All ER 1167 at 1171, KBD</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. Now s 1(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>) makes it clear that the remedy of rescission for misrepresentation is available in such cases. In addition there will also be remedies available for breach of a contractual term.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="6">SECTION 1(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This reverses the rule in <core:emph typestyle="it">Seddon v North Eastern Salt Co Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1905] 1 Ch 326</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> and <core:emph typestyle="it">Angel v Jay</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1911] 1 KB 666</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, whereby an executed contract could not be rescinded for non-fraudulent misrepresentation.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="230">
                  <core:desig value="2">2</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Damages for misrepresentation</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>Where a person has entered into a contract after a misrepresentation has been made to him by another party thereto and as a result thereof he has suffered loss, then, if the person making the misrepresentation would be liable to damages in respect thereof had the misrepresentation been made fraudulently, that person shall be so liable notwithstanding that the misrepresentation was not made fraudulently, unless he proves that he had reasonable ground to believe and did believe up to the time the contract was made that the facts represented were true.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>Where a person has entered into a contract after a misrepresentation has been made to him otherwise that fraudulently, and he would be entitled, by reason of the misrepresentation, to rescind the contract, then, if it is claimed, in any proceedings arising out of the contract, that the contract ought to be or has been rescinded, the court or arbitrator may declare the contract subsisting and award damages in lieu of rescission, if of opinion that it would be equitable to do so, having regard to the nature of the misrepresentation and the loss that would be caused by it if the contract were upheld, as well as to the loss that rescission would cause to the other party.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>Damages may be awarded against a person under subsection (2) of this section whether or not he is liable to damages under subsection (1) thereof, but where he is so liable any award under the said subsection (2) shall be taken into account in assessing his liability under the said subsection (1).</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>[(4)</core:enum>This section does not entitle a person to be paid damages in respect of a misrepresentation if the person has a right to redress under Part 4A of the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008, (SI 2008/1277) in respect of the conduct constituting the misrepresentation.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>Subsection (4) does not prevent a debtor from bringing a claim under section 75(1) of the Consumer Credit Act 1974 against a creditor under a debtor-creditor-supplier agreement in a case where, but for subsection (4), the debtor would have a claim against the supplier in respect of a misrepresentation (and, where section 75 of that Act would otherwise apply, it accordingly applies as if the debtor had a claim against the supplier).]</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section provides statutory rights to damages for contractual negligent misrepresentation (s 2(1)) and enables damages in lieu of rescission to be awarded in cases of non-fraudulent misrepresentation (s 2(2)). Subsection (3) enables damages to be awarded under both sub-s (1) and sub-s (2), but ensures that double damages are not recovered.</core:para>
                     <core:para>In the case of a contract, made on or after 1 October 2014, falling under Pt 4A of the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (SI 2008/1277), see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>1A[54A]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> ff, the consumer is not able to use s 2 and, instead, can seek to unwind the contract, claim a discount and/or claim damages under the 2008 Regulations (s 2(4)).</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Amendment</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>Subsections (4) and (5) were inserted by the Consumer Protection (Amendment) Regulations 2014 (SI 2014/870), reg 5, as of 1 October 2014.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Section 2(1)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This enables a person who has been induced to enter a contract by a negligent misrepresentation to claim damages for the losses suffered. Prior to the Act, the case of <core:emph typestyle="it">Hedley Byrne &amp; Co Ltd v Heller &amp; Partners Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1964] AC 465</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1963] 2 All ER 575, HL</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, established that damages could be claimed for negligent misrepresentations, if a breach of a duty of care involving a ‘special relationship’ could be established. Such a duty could exist and hence, if broken, damages claimed, in cases where a contract had been induced by a negligent misrepresentation, <core:emph typestyle="it">see</core:emph> 
                        <core:emph typestyle="it">Esso Petroleum Co v Mardon</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1976] QB 801</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1976] 2 All ER 5, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. The introduction of s 2(1) removed the need to establish the duty of care between contracting parties and claims for damages for negligent misrepresentations in contract can be based on this subsection.</core:para>
                     <core:para>For this subsection to operate, a misrepresentation has to have been ‘made’ by ‘another party’ to the contract. It does not, therefore, cover non-contractual misrepresentations or misrepresentations by third parties. These types of misrepresentation may, however, fall within <core:emph typestyle="it">Hedley Byrne &amp; Co Ltd v Heller &amp; Partners Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1964] AC 465</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1963] 2 All ER 575, HL</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The phrase ‘another party’ has been held by Mustill J not to give rise to any personal liability under s 2(1) on the part of an agent acting with the express or ostensible authority of the principal nor of any person acting on behalf of the agent. The word ‘person’ in s 2(1) includes the principal, see <core:emph typestyle="it">Resolute Maritime Inc v Nippon Kaiji Kyokai; The Skopas</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1983] 2 All ER 1</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1983] 1 WLR 857, QBD</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> (Commercial Court).</core:para>
                     <core:para>As a consequence of the misrepresentation, the contracting party must have suffered loss. Section 2(1) creates what is known as the ‘fiction of fraud’. It indicates that if damages would be recoverable had the misrepresentation been made fraudulently, then damages will be recoverable without proof of fraud, providing the requirements of the subsection are satisfied. It is suggested that the measure of damages will be the same as those for fraud. This will normally mean damages to put the person in the position he would have been in had the representation not been made, rather than the contractual approach of putting him in the position he would have been had the representation been true.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The <core:emph typestyle="it">Chesneau</core:emph> decision was confirmed in <core:emph typestyle="it">Royscot Trust Ltd v Rogerson</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1991] 3 All ER 294</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1991] 3 WLR 57, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. Here, having accepted that the tortious measure of damages was the correct one to apply in cases under s 2(1), it was necessary to decide whether the measure of damages would be that for fraudulent misrepresentation or for negligence at common law. Balcome LJ was of the opinion that the principles which govern the tort of deceit, ie that even unforeseeable losses providing they were not too remote are recoverable, were the appropriate ones to apply. The case concerned a motor dealer making a negligent misrepresentation to a finance company inducing a hire-purchase agreement with a customer who subsequently wrongfully sold the car to another. The finance company was able to recover from the dealer the difference between the amount the finance company had paid to the dealer and the amount received from the customer.</core:para>
                     <core:para>In assessing a claim for damages under s 2(1) a defence of contributory negligence would be claimable according to <core:emph typestyle="it">Gran Gelato Ltd v Richcliff (Group) Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1992] 1 All ER 865, Ch D</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, although on the facts it was not proven. The court took the view that, as liability under the 1967 Act was founded on negligence, in the sense that the representor was liable unless he had reasonable grounds to believe that the facts represented were true, it would be inconsistent if the defence were available for a claim for a breach of duty of care but not for a claim under s 2(1). Both causes of action arose in the case. Thus the Law Reform (Contributory Negligence) Act 1945, s 1(1) applied, the relevant part of which provides:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘Where any person suffers damage as the result partly of his own fault and partly of the fault of any other person or persons, a claim in respect of that damage shall not be defeated by reason of the fault of the person suffering the damage, but the damages recoverable in respect thereof shall be reduced to such an extent as the court thinks just and equitable having regard to the claimant’s share in the responsibility for the damage…’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">‘Reasonable ground to believe and did believe’</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The representor is liable <core:emph typestyle="it">unless</core:emph> he can prove that he did have reasonable cause to believe and did believe that the facts represented were true. Here the burden of proof is on the representor (unlike under <core:emph typestyle="it">Hedley Byrne</core:emph> where the representee has to prove the negligence of the representor).</core:para>
                     <core:para>In <core:emph typestyle="it">Howard Marine and Dredging Co Ltd v A Ogden &amp; Sons (Excavations) Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1978] QB 574</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1978] 2 All ER 1134, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, the question of ‘reasonable ground to believe, and did believe’ was raised. In a contract for hire of barges, a marine manager misrepresented the payload of barges offered for hire. Although false, the marine manager’s misrepresentation was made honestly, but was made without checking available facts. It was held, by a majority, that the claimants (the employer of the marine manager) had failed to prove the marine manager had ‘reasonable ground to believe’. Lord Justice Bridge at p 596, 1145 stated:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘If the representee proves a misrepresentation which, if fraudulent, would have sounded in damages, the onus passes immediately to the representor to prove that he had reasonable ground to believe the facts represented. In other words the liability of the representor does not depend on his being under a duty of care the extent of which may vary according to the circumstances in which the representation is made. In the course of negotiations leading to a contract the 1967 Act imposes an absolute obligation not to state facts which the representor cannot prove he had reasonable ground to believe.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">‘Up to the time the contract was made’</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The belief in the truth of the facts must continue up to the time the contract is made. Thus, if the representor learns of the falsity of his representations after the representation has been made but before a binding contract is made, he must disclose this.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Damages awarded under s 2(1) can be in addition to rescission. In <core:emph typestyle="it">F and H Entertainments v Leisure Enterprises Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1976) 120 Sol Jo 331, Ch D</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, P were induced to enter into a contract with D to purchase a lease of certain premises by the non-fraudulent representation of D that the landlord had not served a notice reviewing the rent. P went into occupation of the premises and spent £4000 equipping them. On discovering the falsity of D’s representations, P went out of occupation and sought to rescind the contract, repayment of a deposit and damages. It was held (Walton J) that P were entitled to rescind the contract and to the return of their deposit. Damages for expenditure incurred properly and not prematurely or extravagantly were also recoverable.</core:para>
                     <core:para>It has been held in <core:emph typestyle="it">Inntrepreneur Pub Co v Sweeney</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2002] EWHC 1060, (Ch)</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(2002) Times 26 June</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, that the only remedy available under s 2(1) is damages. It is not possible to use the section to defend a claim for injunctive relief.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Note also s 2(2), damages in lieu of rescission, and s 2(3).</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Section 2(2)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This gives the court a discretion to award damages in lieu of rescission for non-fraudulent misrepresentations. A misrepresentation must have been ‘made’ and it must not be fraudulent. Earlier issues of this work stated: the representee must be entitled to rescind, thus it would seem that if a bar operates, for example, lapse of time, s 2(2) cannot be used.</core:para>
                     <core:para>This statement needs to be re-examined in the light of the judgment of Jacob J in <core:emph typestyle="it">Witter (Thomas) Ltd v TBP Industries Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1996) 2 All ER 573</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>12 Tr LR 145</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. Having looked at the Parliamentary debates on s 2, in particular <core:emph typestyle="it">Hansard</core:emph> 20 February 1967, col 1387, Jacob J stated:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘… the Solicitor-General told the House of Commons that it was his view that damages could be awarded under s 2(2) when there was an impossibility of restitution. Accordingly I hold that the power to award damages under s 2(2) does not depend upon an extant right to rescission – it only depends upon a right having existed in the past. Whether it depends upon such a right having existed at any time, or depends upon such a right subsisting at the time when the representee first claims rescission, I do not have to decide … In principle, however, I would have thought that it is enough that at any time a right to rescind subsisted. It is damages in lieu of that right (even if barred by later events or lapse of time) which can be awarded (at p 162).’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>From this it would appear that, as long as there was a right to rescind for misrepresentation at some stage, it does not matter that this right no longer exists at the time of trial, and possibly even at the time the representee first discovers the misrepresentation. If the broadest interpretation is given, it would appear that in <core:emph typestyle="it">every</core:emph> case the court could award damages in lieu of rescission if equitable to do so.</core:para>
                     <core:para>This conclusion is not supported by <core:emph typestyle="it">Zanzibar v British Aerospace (Lancaster House) Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2000] 1 WLR 2333, QBD</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, where, even though a right to rescind had previously existed, it had been lost. Judge Raymond Jack QC re-examined the Parliamentary debates on the wording of s 2(2) and the earlier cases, including the <core:emph typestyle="it">Witter (Thomas) Ltd</core:emph> case. He stated:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘I conclude that both the report of the Law Reform Committee and the manner in which clause 2(2) of the Bill was introduced in the House of Lords make clear that section 2(2) gives the court a discretionary power to hold the contract to be subsisting and to award damages where it would otherwise be obliged to grant rescission or to hold the contract had been rescinded by the representee. The court does not have that power, and does not need to have that power, where rescission is no longer available. In short the power to award damages is an alternative to an order for rescission or the upholding of a prior rescission by the representee if that has occurred.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>The decision in the <core:emph typestyle="it">Witter (Thomas) Ltd</core:emph> case was not followed and it was held that damages could not be claimed by the claimant under s 2(2) as the right to rescind had been lost. A decision of the Court of Appeal, finally to resolve the matter, is clearly needed.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The court or arbitrator has a discretion as to whether or not to award damages; under this subsection there is no <core:emph typestyle="it">right</core:emph> to damages. The decision to award damages must be based on what is equitable. The court has to weigh up the losses caused to the representee if the contract is upheld and balance this against the losses caused to the representor if the contract is rescinded.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Although the Court of Appeal found that there had been no actionable misrepresentation in <core:emph typestyle="it">William Sindall plc v Cambridgeshire County Council</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1994] 3 All ER 932</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, and that therefore no damages could be awarded under sub-s (2) in lieu of rescission, it did examine the effect of sub-s (2). In deciding whether to award damages in lieu of rescission the court had to consider three matters: the nature of the misrepresentation (that is its importance in relation to the subject matter of the transaction), the loss caused if the contract is upheld and the loss caused by rescission. With regard to the damages to be awarded under sub-s (2) Hoffman LJ stated: ‘damages under s 2(2) should never exceed the sum which would have been awarded if the representation had been a warranty’ (at 955). Lord Justice Evans, in discussing whether damages can be awarded to compensate for a decline in market value which occurs after the misrepresentation has been made, explained that this loss was not caused by the misrepresentation and so could not be recovered under sub-s (2). The loss caused by the misrepresentation ‘can be measured by the cost of remedying the defect, or alternatively by the reduced market value attributable to the defect’ (at p 961).</core:para>
                     <core:para>In <core:emph typestyle="it">UCB Corporate Services Ltd v Thomason and Thomason</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2004] EWHC 1164 (Ch)</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2004] 2 All ER (Comm) 774</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> the appellants had entered a waiver agreement with the respondents to avoid bankruptcy, having been unable to meet the terms of two guarantees. The appellants subsequently sought to rescind the waiver agreement and to resurrect the guarantees or to claim damages as a result of a non-fraudulent misrepresentation by the respondents. The court, in considering whether to permit rescission, indicated that the ‘loss’ caused by rescinding, referred to in sub-s (2), covered not only financial loss but also ‘detriment’, as the section requires a balancing exercise to determine what would be ‘equitable’ in the circumstances. The appellants had lost the chance of obtaining more money had the respondents told the truth, but this was dependent upon the financial standing of the respondents which was poor, whereas the respondents faced massive liability if the agreement was rescinded. The court declined to overturn the decision of the trial judge, which was to refuse rescission on the basis that it would be inequitable and, as no damage to the appellants was established, to refuse damages <core:emph typestyle="it">in lieu</core:emph>.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Damages under s 2(2) are <core:emph typestyle="it">in lieu</core:emph> of rescission. Thus a court cannot order rescission or accept that a contract has been rescinded <core:emph typestyle="it">and</core:emph> award damages. Where rescission takes place, the representee can only obtain an indemnity: <core:emph typestyle="it">Whittington v Seale-Hayne</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1900) 82 LT 49, Ch D</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Prior to this Act no damages were possible for entirely innocent misrepresentations (ie non-fraudulent, non-negligent), which did not have contractual force: <core:emph typestyle="it">Redgrave v Hurd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1881) 20 Ch D 1, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. By using s 2(2), the court may now award damages in lieu of rescission for innocent misrepresentations.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Section 2(4)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This subsection only applies to contracts made on or after 1 October 2014. For a right of redress to arise under the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (SI 2008/1277), see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>1A[54A]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> ff. In summary there must be, first, a business to consumer contract for the supply of a product to the consumer; a consumer to business contract for the supply of a product to the trader; or a consumer payment; second, there must have been a prohibited practice, namely a misleading action, in breach of reg 5 of the 2008 Regulations, see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>1A[11]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, or an aggressive practice, in breach of reg 7 of the 2008 Regulations, see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>1A[13]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>; and, third, the prohibited practice must have been a significant factor in the consumer’s decision to enter the contract or make the payment. In such a case, instead of an action for damages under s 2, the consumer can, depending upon the circumstances, seek to unwind the contract, claim a discount on the contract price and/or claim damages for financial loss or for any alarm, distress, or physical inconvenience or discomfort suffered.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Section 2(5)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This makes it clear that, although sub-s (4) would normally remove the right of a consumer to make a claim under s 2 where there is a right of redress under the Consumer Protection from Unfair Trading Regulations 2008 (SI 2008/1277), Pt 4A, see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>1A[54A]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> ff; where there is a claim for a misrepresentation, under the Consumer Credit Act 1974, s 75, see <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>4[137]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, the consumer can still use s 2 to bring such a claim.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-end="240" edpnum-start="231">
                  <core:desig value="3">[3</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Avoidance of provision excluding liability for misrepresentation</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>[[(1)]]</core:enum>If a contract contains a term which would exclude or restrict –</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para2>
                     <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>any liability to which a party to a contract may be subject by reason of any misrepresentation made by him before the contract was made; or</lnb-leg:para2>
                  <lnb-leg:para2>
                     <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>any remedy available to another party to the contract by reason of such a misrepresentation,</lnb-leg:para2>
                  <lnb-leg:para-continued1>that term shall be of no effect except in so far as it satisfies the requirement of reasonableness as stated in section 11(1) of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977; and it is for those claiming that the term satisfies that requirement to show that it does.]</lnb-leg:para-continued1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>[[(2)</core:enum>This section does not apply to a term in a consumer contract within the meaning of Part 2 of the Consumer Rights Act 2015 (but see the provision made about such contracts in section 62 of that Act).]]</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section was inserted by the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, s 8(1) to replace the section originally enacted. It applies to contracts made after 1 February 1978. Those made prior to that date are governed by the original section, where it was left to the court or arbitrator to decide whether or not reliance on a provision was fair and reasonable. The only guidelines provided were ‘according to the circumstances of the case’.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The section, which does not apply to consumer contracts falling under the Consumer Rights Act 2015, Pt 2, see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[6061]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> ff, specifically lays down the test of reasonableness as being s 11(1) of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977 (see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5211]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>). The burden of proof is laid upon the party setting up the plea that the term is reasonable.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Section 11(1) of the 1977 Act states:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘In relation to a contract term, the requirement of reasonableness for the purposes of this Part of this Act, section 3 of the Misrepresentation Act 1967 and section 3 of the Misrepresentation Act (Northern Ireland) 1967 is that the term shall have been a fair and reasonable one to be included having regard to the circumstances which were, or ought reasonably to have been, known to or in the contemplation of the parties when the contract was made.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>The test of reasonableness is on facts which should have been known or in the contemplation of the parties at the time the contract was made.</core:para>
                     <core:para>In <core:emph typestyle="it">Howard Marine and Dredging Co Ltd v Ogden &amp; Sons</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1978] QB 574</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1978] 2 All ER 1134</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> (where, by a majority, the Court of Appeal awarded damages to Ogden’s in respect of a misrepresentation as to the carrying capacity of certain barges) the court also held, by a majority, that Howard’s were not entitled to rely on an exemption clause in the charter-party that acceptance of the vessel was conclusive that she was fit for the intended use and in every other way satisfactory, since such clause, even if it covered the misrepresentation in question, was not ‘fair and reasonable’.</core:para>
                     <core:para>This case was concerned with s 3 as originally enacted.</core:para>
                     <core:para>For a case considering s 3 as substituted by the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, see <core:emph typestyle="it">Walker v Boyle</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1982] 1 All ER 634</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1982] 1 WLR 495, Ch D</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, (see also para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5211]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>). The vendor of a house made a negligent misrepresentation in preliminary inquiries prior to the contract of sale. The contract incorporated the National Conditions of Sale (19th edn), Condition 17 of which sought to preclude the purchaser from rescinding the contract for misrepresentation. The court decided that Condition 17 could not be relied on where the vendor made a negligent misrepresentation about the property when the true facts were within his knowledge. Dillon J then went on to consider whether or not, if Condition 17 did apply, it would satisfy the requirements of s 3. He held that it did not satisfy the requirement of reasonableness and that the purchaser was entitled to rescind the contract, reclaim his deposit, and to damages for loss of interest on his deposit under s 2(1).</core:para>
                     <core:para>A more restrictive version, (in <core:emph typestyle="it">Standard Conditions of Sale</core:emph> (4th edn) which restricted rescission to cases where an error or omission had resulted from fraud or recklessness or where the property would be substantially different from what the purchaser had been led to expect was discussed in <core:emph typestyle="it">Cleaver and Ors v Schyde Investments Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2011] EWCA Civ 929</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. See further notes to s 11 of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977 at para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5211]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The case of <core:emph typestyle="it">Walker v Boyle</core:emph> was discussed in <core:emph typestyle="it">McGrath v Shah</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1987) 57 P &amp; CR 452, Ch D</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. Here the first sentence of Special Condition 9 of the contract for the sale of a house stated: ‘This contract constitutes the entire contract between the parties, and may be varied (whether by way of collateral contract or otherwise) only in writing under the hands of the parties or their solicitors.’ The court decided that this was a contractual provision defining where the contractual terms were to be found and not an exclusion clause. Section 3 only applies to terms directed to the exclusion or restriction of liability for misrepresentation or remedies arising by reason of misrepresentation and so did not apply to the quoted words of Special Condition 9. The court also examined the use of disclaimers in pre-contractual documents eg estate agents’ particulars. If those documents clearly indicated that the particulars did not constitute, nor constitute any part of, an offer or contract then s 3 again did not apply. It is a condition precedent for s 3 to operate that the exclusion clause in question is a term of the contract. If the exclusion clause does not form a term of the contract then s 3 does not apply to it. It appears that non-contractual notices are untouched by s 3 as are contractual provisions which identify what are the terms of the contract.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The general conditions of sale excluding liability for misrepresentation in an auction catalogue failed the test of reasonableness under s 3 in <core:emph typestyle="it">South Western General Property Co Ltd v Marton</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1982) 263 Estates Gazette 1090, QBD</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. The sale concerned building land and it was stated that planning permission had been refused in 1972 because the proposed house was out of character. This wrongly implied that permission would be given for a house in character with the existing development. The purchaser had had no time to make full inquiries and the vendors failed to establish the reasonableness of excluding liability for failing to tell more than part of the facts which were material to the whole contract of sale. (See also para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5211]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>).</core:para>
                     <core:para>In <core:emph typestyle="it">Witter (Thomas) Ltd v TBP Industries Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1996) 2 All ER 573</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>12 Tr LR 145</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> the effect of s 3 was considered in relation to a clause in a contract for the acquisition of a business purporting to avoid liability for any misrepresentations, whether pre-contractual or incorporated into the contract. The clause stated:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘This Agreement sets forth the entire agreement and understanding between the parties or any of them in connection with the business and the sale and purchase described herein. In particular, but without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, the purchaser acknowledges that it has not been induced to enter into this Agreement by any representation or warranty other than the statements contained or referred to in Sch 6.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>The remarks regarding s 3 were <core:emph typestyle="it">obiter</core:emph>, since the court decided that the clause in question did not have the effect claimed by the seller of the business. Mr Justice Jacob referred to the fact that the test in s 3 concerned consideration of the <core:emph typestyle="it">term</core:emph>, not ‘the term so far as it applies to the misrepresentation in question or the kind of misrepresentation in question’ (at pp 170–1). The term was not severable and was either reasonable as a whole or not. It did not distinguish between fraudulent, negligent and innocent misrepresentations. If it excluded liability for one kind of misrepresentation, it did so for all kinds. As it would not be reasonable to exclude liability for fraudulent misrepresentations, the clause was too wide and was unreasonable.</core:para>
                     <core:para>A similar clause in a similar contract was considered by the Court of Appeal in <core:emph typestyle="it">E A Grimstead &amp; Son Ltd v McGarrigan</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1999) 22 Consumer Law Today, Issue 12, p 2, Lexis transcript, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. The Court of Appeal decided that an acknowledgement of non-reliance on pre-contractual statements not included in the contractual documents, could operate as an evidential estoppel. It could prevent the party giving the acknowledgement from asserting, in later litigation, that it was not true. Although it was not necessary to decide on the reasonableness or otherwise of the non-reliance clauses as no actionable misrepresentation had, in fact, been established, the court did express a view on the matter. Assuming that acknowledgements of non-reliance fell within s 3, it was clear that the defendant was only prepared to contract on the basis that the purchaser relied on its own investigations and judgment. Chadwick LJ stated:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘In such a case it seems to me wholly fair and reasonable that the purchaser should seek his remedies (if any) within the four corners of the agreement, and should not be permitted to rely on pre-contractual representations which are, deliberately, not reflected in contractual warranties.</core:para>
                        <core:para>There are, as it seems to me, at least two good reasons why the courts should not refuse to give effect to an acknowledgement of non-reliance in a commercial contract between experienced parties of equal bargaining power – <core:emph typestyle="it">a fortiori</core:emph>, where those parties have the benefit of professional advice. First, it is reasonable to assume that the parties desire commercial certainty. They want to order their affairs on the basis that the bargain between them can be found within the document which they have signed. They want to avoid the uncertainty of litigation based on allegations as to the content of oral discussions at pre-contractual meetings. Second, it is reasonable to assume that the price to be paid reflects the commercial risk which each party – or, more usually, the purchaser – is willing to accept. The risk is determined, in part, at least, by the warranties which the vendor is prepared to give. The tighter the warranties, the less the risk and (in principle, at least) the greater the price which the vendor will require and which the purchaser will be prepared to pay. It is legitimate, and commercially desirable, that both parties should be able to measure the risk, and agree the price, on the basis of the warranties which have been given and accepted.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>This judgment was cited, with approval, by Clarke LJ in <core:emph typestyle="it">National Westminster Bank v Utrecht-America Finance Co</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2001] EWCA Civ 658</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2001] 3 All ER 733</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> at [60]–[61]; pp 751–2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>In <core:emph typestyle="it">Skipskredittforeningen v Emperor Navigation SA</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1998] 1 Lloyd’s Rep 66, QBD</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> (Commercial Court), the court had to decide whether or not a clause seeking to exclude a set-off could be regarded as falling under s 3. The key issue was whether a set-off was a ‘remedy’ under para (<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>). The court referred to the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, s 13 (see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5213]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>) and the extended definition of a ‘remedy’ provided there and also the decision in <core:emph typestyle="it">Stewart Gill Ltd v Horatio Myer &amp; Co Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1992] QB 600</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[1992] 2 All ER 257, CA</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[5213]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. It concluded that, although Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, s 13 did not apply to s 3, there was no reason why the word ‘remedy’ in s 3 should be interpreted differently from the interpretation under the 1977 Act. A set-off is, therefore, a ‘remedy’ for the purposes of s 3.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Mance J ruled that s 3 could only invalidate a clause in respect to claims based on misrepresentation. For a breach of contract claim the different scheme of the 1977 Act would have to be used. He referred to the <core:emph typestyle="it">Stewart Gill</core:emph> decision, from which it appeared that ‘if a clause fails to satisfy the requirement of reasonableness in any respect then it fails in all respects however immaterial may be the respects in which it is unreasonable to the particular case before the court’ (at p 75). Having seen no reason to distinguish this decision, he continued:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘The consequence of the approach adopted in <core:emph typestyle="it">Stewart Gill</core:emph> is … that the court may hear arguments that a term is or may be unreasonable (and so wholly void in relation to misrepresentation or breach of contract claims, as the case may be) for reasons or in respects that have nothing to do with the facts of the actual case. Assuming that the whole term will be invalid in this way if it fails the requirement of reasonableness, the court should, I think, take care to consider the clause as a whole in the light of the circumstances when the contract was made, in order to judge in the round whether it satisfies the requirement of reasonableness. The court should not be too ready to focus on remote possibilities or to accept arguments that a clause fails the test by reference to relatively uncommon or unlikely situations.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>Having considered the reasonableness of reliance on the clause, the court upheld the clause.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The case of <core:emph typestyle="it">Trident Turboprop (Dublin) Ltd v First Flight Couriers Ltd</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2009] EWCA Civ 290</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2010] QB 86</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>[2009] 2 All ER (Comm) 1050</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>, decided that s 3 does not apply to international supply contracts by virtue of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, s 26.</core:para>
                     <core:para>For the Consumer Rights Act 2015, Pt 2, see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[6061]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite> ff and for s 62, see para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[6062]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Amendment</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The material in double square brackets at the start of the section and sub-s (2) were inserted by the Consumer Rights Act 2015, s 75 and Sch 4, para 1, for contracts made on or after 1 October 2015 (Consumer Rights Act 2015 (Commencement No 3, Transitional Provisions, Savings and Consequential Amendments) Order 2015 (SI 2015/1630), art 3(<core:emph typestyle="it">g</core:emph>)). For transitional provisions and savings, see Commencement Order, art 6, at para <lnci:cite type="paragraph-ref">
                           <lnci:content>[6177]</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Position prior to 1 October 2015</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The wording of s 3 prior to 1 October 2015 was:</core:para>
                     <core:list type="plain">
                        <core:listitem>
                           <core:para>If a contract contains a term which would exclude or restrict –</core:para>
                           <core:list type="lower-alpha">
                              <core:listitem>
                                 <core:para>any liability to which a party to a contract may be subject by reason of any misrepresentation made by him before the contract was made; or</core:para>
                              </core:listitem>
                              <core:listitem>
                                 <core:para>any remedy available to another party to the contract by reason of such a misrepresentation,</core:para>
                              </core:listitem>
                           </core:list>
                        </core:listitem>
                        <core:listitem>
                           <core:para>that term shall be of no effect except in so far as it satisfies the requirement of reasonableness as stated in section 11(1) of the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977; and it is for those claiming that the term satisfies that requirement to show that it does.</core:para>
                        </core:listitem>
                     </core:list>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="241">
                  <core:desig value="4">4</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Amendments of Sale of Goods Act 1893</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>[<core:emph typestyle="it">Repealed by the Sale of Goods Act 1979, s 63 and Sch 3 as of 1 January 1980</core:emph>]</lnb-leg:para1>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="242">
                  <core:desig value="5">5</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Saving for past transactions</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>Nothing in this Act shall apply in relation to any misrepresentation or contract of sale which is made before the commencement of this Act.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The reference to ‘contract of sale’ concerned s 4, now repealed.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
               <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243">
                  <core:desig value="6">6</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Short title, commencement and extent</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This Act may be cited as the Misrepresentation Act 1967.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>This Act shall come into operation at the expiration of the period of one month beginning with the date on which it is passed.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>This Act … does not extend to Scotland.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <lnb-leg:para1>
                     <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>This Act does not extend to Northern Ireland.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Amendment</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The words ‘except section 4(2)’ were deleted from sub-s (3) by the Sale of Goods Act 1979, s 63 and Sch 3 as of 1 January 1980, with the repeal of s 4.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Subsection (2)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The Act received Royal Assent on 22 March 1967; it therefore came into operation on 22 April 1967.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:provision>
            </lnb-leg:main>
         </lnb-leg:act>
      </lnb-leg:legislation>
      <lnb-leg:legislation>
         <lnb-leg:act acronym="CI(D and R)A 2012" origin="uk">
            <header:metadata type="legislation">
               <header:metadata-item name="normcite" value="2012_6a"/>
            </header:metadata>
            <lnb-leg:prelims>
               <lnb-leg:officialname>
                  <core:title>Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012</core:title>
               </lnb-leg:officialname>
               <lnb-leg:officialnum>Chapter 6</lnb-leg:officialnum>
               <lnb-leg:longtitle>An Act to make provision about disclosure and representations in connection with consumer insurance contracts.</lnb-leg:longtitle>
               <lnb-leg:royal-assent>
                  <core:date>[8th March 2012]</core:date>
               </lnb-leg:royal-assent>
               <core:comment type="commentary">
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Preliminary Notes</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Scope of the Act </core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para edpnum-start="243A">The Act gives effect, with minor modifications, to the recommendations set out in the Law Commission and the Scottish Law Commission’s 2009 joint report ‘<core:emph typestyle="it">Consumer Insurance Law: Pre-Contract Disclosure and Misrepresentation</core:emph>’ (Law Com No 319; Scot Law Com No 219). </core:para>
                  <core:para>The Marine Insurance Act 1906 (which is applied to all forms of insurance, including consumer insurance), requires that the insured person must disclose every matter that would be material to the insurer’s decision to insure. Failure to do this permits the insurer to avoid the contract and refuse all claims under it, even where the insured person is not aware of what the insurer would consider material.</core:para>
                  <core:para>Section 2 of the 2012 Act replaces the duty to volunteer material information with a duty on consumers to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation during pre-contractual negotiations.</core:para>
                  <core:para>If a consumer breaches this duty and this misrepresentation induces the insurer to enter the contract, s 4 enables the insurer to have a remedy. The nature of the insurer’s remedy is specified in Sch 1 and depends on the nature of the consumer’s misrepresentation. If a consumer makes a deliberate or reckless misrepresentation, the Act permits the insurer to treat the contract as if it never existed and refuse all claims. If, when answering questions posed by an insurer, a consumer answers carelessly, the Act provides that the insurer may have a remedy according to whether it would have entered into the contract on different terms. If it would not have entered into the contract at all it may refuse all claims but it must return the premiums paid. If it would have entered into the contract on different terms, the contract may be taken to include those different terms.</core:para>
                  <core:para>If the premium would have been higher this may have consequences for the amount of any claim. If the consumer acts with reasonable care, the insurer must pay the claim in full.</core:para>
                  <core:para>Section 7 makes provision for a situation where a member of a group insurance policy makes a misrepresentation. Where this happens the misrepresentation will only have consequences for the cover of that member and not for the policy as a whole.</core:para>
                  <core:para>Section 8 makes provision in relation to insurance taken out by a consumer on another person’s life. Previously, the person whose life was being insured did not normally owe a duty of care when providing information, because they were not a party to the contract. The Act changes this so that when answering questions posed by the insurance company, the person whose life is being insured has a duty to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation. If that individual makes a misrepresentation, the insurer will have the same remedies they would have had if the consumer taking out the policy made the misrepresentation.</core:para>
                  <core:para>Section 9 expressly preserves normal agency law, which states that a party is responsible for the actions of their own agent. Schedule 2 sets out a framework for deciding whether, for the purposes of the Act, the intermediary acts as an agent for the insurer or for the consumer.</core:para>
                  <core:para>Section 11 disapplies ss 18, 19 and 20 of the Marine Insurance Act 1906 in respect of consumer insurance contracts, as defined in the Act. Section 11 also disapplies any common law rule to the same effect as these sections.</core:para>
                  <core:para>The Road Traffic Act 1988, s 152(2) and the Road Traffic (Northern Ireland) Order 1981, (SI 1981/154 (NI)), art 98A, are amended by s 11 because they relate to insurance companies avoiding motor insurance contracts where the insured has made a non-disclosure or misrepresentation.</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Extent</core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>The Act, apart from the provisions listed in s 12(7), applies to England and Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.</core:para>
                  <core:generic-hd level="5">Commencement </core:generic-hd>
                  <core:para>Sections 1 and 12 of the Act came into force on 8 March 2012 (s 12(2)). The remainder of the Act came into force on 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450).</core:para>
               </core:comment>
            </lnb-leg:prelims>
            <lnb-leg:main>
               <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                  <core:title>Main definitions</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243B">
                     <core:desig value="1">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">1</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Main definitions</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>In this Act—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>“consumer insurance contract” means a contract of insurance between—</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para3>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>an individual who enters into the contract wholly or mainly for purposes unrelated to the individual’s trade, business or profession, and</lnb-leg:para3>
                     <lnb-leg:para3>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>a person who carries on the business of insurance and who becomes a party to the contract by way of that business (whether or not in accordance with permission for the purposes of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000);</lnb-leg:para3>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>“consumer” means the individual who enters into a consumer insurance contract, or proposes to do so;</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>“insurer” means the person who is, or would become, the other party to a consumer insurance contract.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force on 8 March 2012, by virtue of s 12(2). It provides definitions of the main terms used in the Act.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The definition of a ‘consumer insurance contract’ is based on the status of the persons who enter into the contract. The contract must be between a consumer and an insurer, who is acting in the course of a business.</core:para>
                     <core:para>A ‘consumer’ must be an ‘individual’, that is a natural person, who is acting wholly or mainly for non-business purposes. According to the <core:emph typestyle="it">Explanatory Notes on the draft Bill</core:emph> at para 18:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘The definition expressly provides for mixed use contracts. Where a policy covers some non-business and some business use, the main purpose of the insurance needs to be considered. For example, insurance would be considered to be “consumer insurance” if vehicle insurance covers a limited amount of business use, or if home contents insurance covers some business equipment.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:heading>
               <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                  <core:title>Pre-contract and pre-variation information</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243C">
                     <core:desig value="2">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">2</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Disclosure and representations before contract or variation</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This section makes provision about disclosure and representations by a consumer to an insurer before a consumer insurance contract is entered into or varied.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>It is the duty of the consumer to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation to the insurer.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>A failure by the consumer to comply with the insurer’s request to confirm or amend particulars previously given is capable of being a misrepresentation for the purposes of this Act (whether or not it could be apart from this subsection).</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>The duty set out in subsection (2) replaces any duty relating to disclosure or representations by a consumer to an insurer which existed in the same circumstances before this Act applied.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>Accordingly—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>any rule of law to the effect that a consumer insurance contract is one of the utmost good faith is modified to the extent required by the provisions of this Act, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the application of section 17 of the Marine Insurance Act 1906 (contracts of marine insurance are of utmost good faith), in relation to a contract of marine insurance which is a consumer insurance contract, is subject to the provisions of this Act.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>It abolishes the duty of disclosure in consumer insurance contracts and replaces it with the duty ‘to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation’. The effect of this is to removes the consumer’s duty to volunteer information to the insurer. Instead, consumers are required to answer insurers’ questions honestly and to take reasonable care that their replies are accurate; they must do so honestly and carefully.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Subsection (1) </core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The consumer’s duty applies to pre-contractual negotiations when making a new insurance contract or varying an existing contract. If an insurance contract is renewed, this is regarded as making a new contract, so the duty will also arise on renewals.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Subsections (2) and (3)</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The duty placed on the consumer is to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation to the insurer. The case law on the general law of misrepresentation is of relevance here. The <core:emph typestyle="it">Explanatory Notes on the draft Bill</core:emph> draw attention to the following aspect, at para 23:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘In particular, even though it is literally true, a statement may amount to a misrepresentation because it is incomplete. (See <core:emph typestyle="it">Winter v Irish Life Assurance plc</core:emph> 
                           <lnci:cite type="case">
                              <lnci:content>[1995] 2 Lloyd’s Rep 274</lnci:content>
                           </lnci:cite>)’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>By virtue of sub-s (3), a failure to reply to a request to confirm or amend information that has previously been given will also amount to a misrepresentation. This is particularly relevant when contracts are renewed.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243D">
                     <core:desig value="3">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">3</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Reasonable care</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>Whether or not a consumer has taken reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation is to be determined in the light of all the relevant circumstances.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>The following are examples of things which may need to be taken into account in making a determination under subsection (1)—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>the type of consumer insurance contract in question, and its target market,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>any relevant explanatory material or publicity produced or authorised by the insurer,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>how clear, and how specific, the insurer’s questions were,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">d</core:emph>)</core:enum>in the case of a failure to respond to the insurer’s questions in connection with the renewal or variation of a consumer insurance contract, how clearly the insurer communicated the importance of answering those questions (or the possible consequences of failing to do so),</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">e</core:emph>)</core:enum>whether or not an agent was acting for the consumer.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>The standard of care required is that of a reasonable consumer: but this is subject to subsections (4) and (5).</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>If the insurer was, or ought to have been, aware of any particular characteristics or circumstances of the actual consumer, those are to be taken into account.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>A misrepresentation made dishonestly is always to be taken as showing lack of reasonable care.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>It provides an explanation of what is meant by taking ‘reasonable care’. Subsection (1) indicates that when deciding whether a consumer has taken reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation, all relevant circumstances are to be taken into account. Factors which may be considered are indicated in sub-s (2). This is an indicative and non-exhaustive list. Other factors may be relevant in some circumstances.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Subsection (3) imposes an objective test in determining whether or not the consumer has taken reasonable care, subject to the provisions of sub-ss (4) and (5). The <core:emph typestyle="it">Explanatory Notes on the draft Bill</core:emph> provide further explanation, at para 28:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘This test does not usually take into account any particular characteristics of the actual consumer, such as their age or knowledge of English. The notion of “reasonableness” is a commonly used concept in English law to provide an objective but flexible standard against which any individual's conduct can be measured. The reasonable consumer denotes an average consumer with no special skills or knowledge taking into account the examples in subsection (2).’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:para>Subsection (4) deals with the situation where an insurer knew, or ought to have known, about a consumer’s particular characteristics or circumstances, in which case these must be taken into account. This could include, for example, knowledge of visual impairment, making it difficult for the consumer to read small print on an application form.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Subsection (5) provides that acting dishonestly is always a breach of the duty.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:heading>
               <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                  <core:title>Qualifying misrepresentations</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243E">
                     <core:desig value="4">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">4</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Qualifying misrepresentations: definition and remedies</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>An insurer has a remedy against a consumer for a misrepresentation made by the consumer before a consumer insurance contract was entered into or varied only if—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>the consumer made the misrepresentation in breach of the duty set out in section 2(2), and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurer shows that without the misrepresentation, that insurer would not have entered into the contract (or agreed to the variation) at all, or would have done so only on different terms.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>A misrepresentation for which the insurer has a remedy against the consumer is referred to in this Act as a “qualifying misrepresentation”.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>The only such remedies available are set out in Schedule 1.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>The section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>This section explains when an insurer will have a remedy for misrepresentation by a consumer. The insurer must prove, on the balance of probabilities, that (a) the consumer made a misrepresentation in breach of the duty laid down in s 2(2) to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation and (b) had the insurer known the true facts, it would not have entered into the contract or agreed the variation at all or would only have done so on different terms from those agreed. If these conditions are met then, under sub-s (2), the misrepresentation is a ‘qualifying misrepresentation’ and the remedies set out in Sch 1 are available to the insurer.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243F">
                     <core:desig value="5">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">5</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Qualifying misrepresentations: classification and presumptions</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>For the purposes of this Act, a qualifying misrepresentation (see section 4(2)) is either—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>deliberate or reckless, or</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>careless.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>A qualifying misrepresentation is deliberate or reckless if the consumer—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>knew that it was untrue or misleading, or did not care whether or not it was untrue or misleading, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>knew that the matter to which the misrepresentation related was relevant to the insurer, or did not care whether or not it was relevant to the insurer.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>A qualifying misrepresentation is careless if it is not deliberate or reckless.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>It is for the insurer to show that a qualifying misrepresentation was deliberate or reckless.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>But it is to be presumed, unless the contrary is shown—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>that the consumer had the knowledge of a reasonable consumer, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>that the consumer knew that a matter about which the insurer asked a clear and specific question was relevant to the insurer.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>By sub-s (1), a distinction is drawn between misrepresentations which are (a) deliberate or reckless, and (b) careless. Subsection (2) defines what a deliberate or reckless qualifying misrepresentation is by reference to the meaning of ‘fraud’ derived from the tort of deceit case: <core:emph typestyle="it">Derry v Peek</core:emph> 
                        <lnci:cite type="case">
                           <lnci:content>(1889) LR 14 App Cas 337</lnci:content>
                        </lnci:cite>. If a qualifying misrepresentation is neither deliberate nor reckless then, by sub-s (3), it is treated as a careless misrepresentation. The burden is on the insurer to show that a qualifying misrepresentation is deliberate or reckless (sub-s (4)). Two presumptions are set out in sub-s (5). If the presumptions apply, the burden of proof is reversed. The <core:emph typestyle="it">Explanatory Notes on the draft Bill</core:emph> illustrate this, at para 40:</core:para>
                     <core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>‘The effect of the presumptions may be illustrated by an example, in which a consumer fails to mention a heart attack in response to a clear and specific question. As most reasonable people would normally know that they had suffered a heart attack, the insurer does not need to prove that the consumer acted deliberately or recklessly. Instead it is up to the consumer to show that he or she did not know about the heart attack, or did not understand the question. Thus the consumer might explain that they had confused a minor heart attack with another condition, or might provide other evidence of lack of understanding.’</core:para>
                     </core:blockquote>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘qualifying misrepresentation’, see s 4. For ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:heading>
               <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                  <core:title>Specific issues</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243G">
                     <core:desig value="6">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">6</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Warranties and representations</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This section applies to representations made by a consumer—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>in connection with a proposed consumer insurance contract, or</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in connection with a proposed variation to a consumer insurance contract.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>Such a representation is not capable of being converted into a warranty by means of any provision of the consumer insurance contract (or of the terms of the variation), or of any other contract (and whether by declaring the representation to form the basis of the contract or otherwise).</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The section abolishes ‘basis of contract’ clauses in consumer insurance contracts, whereby insurers include a declaration on an insurance proposal form or policy stating that the consumer warrants the accuracy of the answers or that the answers form the basis of the contract.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, and ‘consumer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243H">
                     <core:desig value="7">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">7</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Group insurance</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This section applies where—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>a contract of insurance is entered into by a person (“A”) in order to provide cover for another person (“C”), or is varied or extended so as to do so,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>C is not a party to the contract,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>so far as the cover for C is concerned, the contract would have been a consumer insurance contract if entered into by C rather than by A, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">d</core:emph>)</core:enum>C provided information directly or indirectly to the insurer before the contract was entered into, or before it was varied or extended to provide cover for C.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>So far as the cover for C is concerned—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>sections 2 and 3 apply in relation to disclosure and representations by C to the insurer as if C were proposing to enter into a consumer insurance contract for the relevant cover with the insurer, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>subject to subsections (3) to (5) and the modifications in relation to the insurer’s remedies set out in Part 3 of Schedule 1, the remainder of this Act applies in relation to the cover for C as if C had entered into a consumer insurance contract for that cover with the insurer.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>Section 4(1)(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>) applies as if it read as follows—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:amending-text>
                        <lnb-leg:para2>
                           <core:enum>“(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurer shows that without the misrepresentation, that insurer would not have agreed to provide cover for C at all, or would have done so only on different terms.”</lnb-leg:para2>
                     </lnb-leg:amending-text>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>If there is more than one C, a breach on the part of one of them of the duty imposed (by virtue of subsection (2)(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)) by section 2(2) does not affect the contract so far as it relates to the others.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>Nothing in this section affects any duty owed by A to the insurer, or any remedy which the insurer may have against A for breach of such a duty.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>In the case of a group insurance scheme, as defined under sub-s (1), if a group member makes a misrepresentation, sub-ss (2) and (3) have the effect of applying the provisions of the Act to give the insurer a remedy, where the consumer acted without reasonable care in supplying information to the insurer and the insurer would not have provided cover, or would only have provided it on different terms, if the insurer had known the true position.</core:para>
                     <core:para>It is only the cover of the individual consumer who has made the misrepresentation which is affected, not the contract as a whole, under sub-s (4).</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243I">
                     <core:desig value="8">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">8</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Insurance on life of another</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This section applies in relation to a consumer insurance contract for life insurance on the life of an individual (“L”) who is not a party to the contract.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>If this section applies—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>information provided to the insurer by L is to be treated for the purposes of this Act as if it were provided by the person who is the party to the contract, but</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in relation to such information, if anything turns on the state of mind, knowledge, circumstances or characteristics of the individual providing the information, it is to be determined by reference to L and not the party to the contract.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>This section applies when a consumer takes out life insurance on the life of another person, ‘L’, and L provides information to the insurer. Any representations made by L are treated as though they were made by the person who is actually taking out the policy. L is, therefore, under a duty to take reasonable care when answering the insurer’s questions and it is L’s state of mind etc which is relevant with regard to these answers. The insurer will have a remedy against the consumer where either the consumer or L fails to take reasonable care in providing information to the insurer.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243J">
                     <core:desig value="9">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">9</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Agents</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>Schedule 2 applies for determining, for the purposes of this Act only, whether an agent through whom a consumer insurance contract is effected is the agent of the consumer or of the insurer.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>The section provides that Sch 2 is to be used to decide, when an agent is used, whether that agent is acting as agent for the consumer or as agent for the insurer for the purposes of this Act. </core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243K">
                     <core:desig value="10">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">10</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Contracting out</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>A term of a consumer insurance contract, or of any other contract, which would put the consumer in a worse position as respects the matters mentioned in subsection (2) than the consumer would be in by virtue of the provisions of this Act is to that extent of no effect.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>The matters are—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>disclosure and representations by the consumer to the insurer before the contract is entered into or varied, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>any remedies for qualifying misrepresentations (see section 4(2)).</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>This section does not apply in relation to a contract for the settlement of a claim arising under a consumer insurance contract.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Any term in a consumer insurance contract or any other contract which would put the consumer in a worse position with regard to disclosure and representations made by the consumer to the insurer prior to entering or varying the contract and remedies for qualifying misrepresentations is void. It is, however, permitted for consumer insurance contracts to include terms requiring disclosure <core:emph typestyle="it">after</core:emph> the contract is concluded. The section does not apply to contracts for settlement of claims which arise under a consumer insurance contract (sub-s (3)).</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘qualifying misrepresentation’, see s 4. For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:heading>
               <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                  <core:title>Final provision</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243L">
                     <core:desig value="11">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">11</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Consequential provision</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>Any rule of law to the same effect as the following is abolished in relation to consumer insurance contracts—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>section 18 of the Marine Insurance Act 1906 (disclosure by assured),</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>section 19 of that Act (disclosure by agent effecting insurance),</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>section 20 of that Act (representations pending negotiation of contract).</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>The Marine Insurance Act 1906 is amended as follows—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>in section 18, at the end add—</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:amending-text>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>
                           <core:enum>“(6)</core:enum>This section does not apply in relation to a contract of marine insurance if it is a consumer insurance contract within the meaning of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012.”;</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:amending-text>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in section 19, the existing text becomes subsection (1), and after that add—</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:amending-text>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>
                           <core:enum>“(2)</core:enum>This section does not apply in relation to a contract of marine insurance if it is a consumer insurance contract within the meaning of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012.”;</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:amending-text>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>in section 20, at the end add—</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:amending-text>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>
                           <core:enum>“(8)</core:enum>This section does not apply in relation to a contract of marine insurance if it is a consumer insurance contract within the meaning of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012.”.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:amending-text>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>In section 152 of the Road Traffic Act 1988 (exceptions to duty of insurers to satisfy judgment against persons insured against third-party risks), in subsection (2)—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>in paragraph (<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>), after “avoid it” insert “either under the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 or, if that Act does not apply,”;</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in paragraph (<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>), after “policy or security” insert “under that Act or”, and for “it” substitute “the policy or security”.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>In Article 98A of the Road Traffic (Northern Ireland) Order 1981, (SI 1981/154 (NI)) (exceptions to duty of insurers to satisfy judgment against persons insured against third-party risks), in paragraph (2)—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>in sub-paragraph (<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>), after “avoid it” insert “either under the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 or, if that Act does not apply,”;</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in sub-paragraph (<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>), after “policy or security” insert “under that Act or”, and for “it” substitute “the policy or security”.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>Amendments are made to the Marine Insurance Act 1906, the Road Traffic Act 1988 and the Road Traffic (Northern Ireland) Order 1981, (SI 1981/154 (NI)) to abolish certain existing rules in relation to consumer insurance contracts, which are now governed by the provisions of this Act instead.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
                  <lnb-leg:provision edpnum-start="243M">
                     <core:desig value="12">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">12</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <core:title>
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">Short title, commencement, application and extent</core:emph>
                     </core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This Act may be cited as the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>Section 1 and this section come into force on the day on which this Act is passed, but otherwise this Act comes into force on such day as the Treasury may by order made by statutory instrument appoint.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>An order under subsection (2) may not appoint a day sooner than the end of the period of 1 year beginning with the day on which this Act is passed.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>This Act applies only in relation to consumer insurance contracts entered into, and variations to consumer insurance contracts agreed, after the Act comes into force.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para-continued1>In the case of group insurance (see section 7), that includes the provision of cover for C by means of an insurance contract entered into by A after the Act comes into force, or varied or extended so as to do so after the Act comes into force.</lnb-leg:para-continued1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>Nothing in this Act affects the circumstances in which a person is bound by the acts or omissions of that person’s agent.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(6)</core:enum>Apart from the provisions listed in subsection (7), this Act extends to England and Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(7)</core:enum>In section 11—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>subsection (3) extends to England and Wales and Scotland only;</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>subsection (4) extends to Northern Ireland only.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This section came into force on 8 March 2012.</core:para>
                     <core:para>An Order, made under sub-s (2), brought the remainder of the Act into force from 6 April 2013, see the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450).</core:para>
                     <core:para>Subsection (5) retains the existing rules of agency law, whereby a person is responsible for the actions of his own agent.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:heading>
            </lnb-leg:main>
            <lnb-leg:schedule-grp>
               <lnb-leg:schedule edpnum-start="243N">
                  <core:desig value="1">Schedule 1</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Insurers’ Remedies for Qualifying Misrepresentations</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:enabling-legislation>Section 4(3)</lnb-leg:enabling-legislation>
                  <lnb-leg:heading level="1">
                     <core:desig value="1">Part 1</core:desig>
                     <core:title>Contracts</core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                        <core:title>General</core:title>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="1">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">1</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>This Part of this Schedule applies in relation to qualifying misrepresentations made in connection with consumer insurance contracts (for variations to them, see Part 2).</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                     </lnb-leg:heading>
                     <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                        <core:title>Deliberate or reckless misrepresentations</core:title>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="2">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">2</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>If a qualifying misrepresentation was deliberate or reckless, the insurer—</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>may avoid the contract and refuse all claims, and</lnb-leg:para2>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>need not return any of the premiums paid, except to the extent (if any) that it would be unfair to the consumer to retain them.</lnb-leg:para2>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                     </lnb-leg:heading>
                     <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                        <core:title>Careless misrepresentations—claims</core:title>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="3">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">3</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>If the qualifying misrepresentation was careless, paragraphs 4 to 8 apply in relation to any claim.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="4">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">4</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>The insurer’s remedies are based on what it would have done if the consumer had complied with the duty set out in section 2(2), and paragraphs 5 to 8 are to be read accordingly.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="5">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">5</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>If the insurer would not have entered into the consumer insurance contract on any terms, the insurer may avoid the contract and refuse all claims, but must return the premiums paid.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="6">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">6</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>If the insurer would have entered into the consumer insurance contract, but on different terms (excluding terms relating to the premium), the contract is to be treated as if it had been entered into on those different terms if the insurer so requires.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="7">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">7</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>In addition, if the insurer would have entered into the consumer insurance contract (whether the terms relating to matters other than the premium would have been the same or different), but would have charged a higher premium, the insurer may reduce proportionately the amount to be paid on a claim.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="8">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">8</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>“Reduce proportionately” means that the insurer need pay on the claim only X% of what it would otherwise have been under an obligation to pay under the terms of the contract (or, if applicable, under the different terms provided for by virtue of paragraph 6), where—</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>X = (Premium actually charged/Higher premium) × 100</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                     </lnb-leg:heading>
                     <lnb-leg:heading level="x">
                        <core:title>Careless misrepresentations—treatment of contract for the future</core:title>
                        <lnb-leg:provision>
                           <core:desig value="9">
                              <core:emph typestyle="bf">9</core:emph>
                           </core:desig>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>This paragraph—</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>applies if the qualifying misrepresentation was careless, but</lnb-leg:para2>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>does not relate to any outstanding claim.</lnb-leg:para2>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>Paragraphs 5 and 6 (as read with paragraph 4) apply as they apply where a claim has been made.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>Paragraph 7 (as read with paragraph 4) applies in relation to a claim yet to be made as it applies in relation to a claim which has been made.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>If by virtue of sub-paragraph (2) or (3), the insurer would have either (or both) of the rights conferred by paragraph 6 or 7, the insurer may—</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>give notice to that effect to the consumer, or</lnb-leg:para2>
                           <lnb-leg:para2>
                              <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>terminate the contract by giving reasonable notice to the consumer.</lnb-leg:para2>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(5)</core:enum>But the insurer may not terminate a contract under sub-paragraph (4)(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>) if it is wholly or mainly one of life insurance.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(6)</core:enum>If the insurer gives notice to the consumer under sub-paragraph (4)(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>), the consumer may terminate the contract by giving reasonable notice to the insurer.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(7)</core:enum>If either party terminates the contract under this paragraph, the insurer must refund any premiums paid for the terminated cover in respect of the balance of the contract term.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(8)</core:enum>Termination of the contract under this paragraph does not affect the treatment of any claim arising under the contract in the period before termination.</lnb-leg:para1>
                           <lnb-leg:para1>
                              <core:enum>(9)</core:enum>Nothing in this paragraph affects any contractual right to terminate the contract.</lnb-leg:para1>
                        </lnb-leg:provision>
                     </lnb-leg:heading>
                  </lnb-leg:heading>
                  <lnb-leg:heading level="1">
                     <core:desig value="2">Part 2</core:desig>
                     <core:title>Variations</core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="10">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">10</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>This Part of this Schedule applies in relation to qualifying misrepresentations made in connection with variations to consumer insurance contracts.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="11">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">11</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>If the subject-matter of a variation can reasonably be treated separately from the subject-matter of the rest of the contract, Part 1 of this Schedule applies (with any necessary modifications) in relation to the variation as it applies in relation to a contract.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="12">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">12</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>Otherwise, Part 1 applies (with any necessary modifications) as if the qualifying misrepresentation had been made in relation to the whole contract (for this purpose treated as including the variation) rather than merely in relation to the variation.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                  </lnb-leg:heading>
                  <lnb-leg:heading level="1">
                     <core:desig value="3">Part 3</core:desig>
                     <core:title>Modifications for Group Insurance</core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="13">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">13</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>Part 1 is to be read subject to the following modifications in relation to cover provided for C under a group insurance contract as mentioned in section 7 (and in this Part “A” and “C” mean the same as in that section).</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="14">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">14</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>References to the consumer insurance contract (however described) are to that part of the contract which provides for cover for C.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="15">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">15</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>References to claims and premiums are to claims and premiums in relation to that cover.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="16">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">16</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>The reference to the consumer is to be read—</lnb-leg:para1>
                        <lnb-leg:para2>
                           <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>in paragraph 2(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>), as a reference to whoever paid the premiums, or the part of them that related to the cover for C,</lnb-leg:para2>
                        <lnb-leg:para2>
                           <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>in paragraph 9(4) and (6), as a reference to A.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                  </lnb-leg:heading>
                  <lnb-leg:heading level="1">
                     <core:desig value="4">Part 4</core:desig>
                     <core:title>Supplementary</core:title>
                     <lnb-leg:provision>
                        <core:desig value="17">
                           <core:emph typestyle="bf">17</core:emph>
                        </core:desig>
                        <lnb-leg:para1>Section 84 of the Marine Insurance Act 1906 (return of premium for failure of consideration) is to be read subject to the provisions of this Schedule in relation to contracts of marine insurance which are consumer insurance contracts.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     </lnb-leg:provision>
                     <core:comment type="commentary">
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>This schedule came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                        <core:para>Schedule 1 details the remedies available to insurers when there has been a qualifying misrepresentation made in a consumer insurance contract.</core:para>
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">Part 1</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>This deals with the remedies available to an insurer for qualifying misrepresentations made prior to a consumer insurance contract being made or renewed.</core:para>
                        <core:para>If there has been a deliberate or reckless misrepresentation, the insurer is entitled to avoid the contract and refuse all claims, under para 2. The insurer can also retain any premiums, unless it would be unfair to do so.</core:para>
                        <core:para>If there has been a careless misrepresentation, the remedies available to the insurer are detailed in paras 3-8. The remedies are based on what the insurer would have done had the consumer complied with their duty to take reasonable care not to make a misrepresentation. If the insurer would not have entered into the contract at all, the insurer can avoid the contract and refuse to pay all claims, but must repay all premiums paid by the consumer (para 5).</core:para>
                        <core:para>If the insurer would still have entered a contract, but on different terms and those terms do not relate to the premium, paragraph 6 enables the insurer to treat the contract as having been entered into on those different terms. The <core:emph typestyle="it">Explanatory Notes on the draft Bill</core:emph> illustrate this, at para 73:</core:para>
                        <core:blockquote>
                           <core:para>‘If, for example, the insurer would have included an exemption clause or imposed an excess, the claim would be treated as if the contract included that exemption clause or excess.’</core:para>
                        </core:blockquote>
                        <core:para>If the insurer would have charged a higher premium, the insurer can reduce the claim proportionately, under para 7. The formula for calculating the reduction is contained in para 8. It is possible for both paras 6 and 7 to apply, whereby the consumer would receive a proportionate settlement of that part of the claim that falls within the modified contract terms.</core:para>
                        <core:para>Paragraph 9 applies to the future of the insurance contract where there has been a careless qualifying misrepresentation. If the insurer would not have entered into the contract at all, then the insurer can choose to avoid the contract (and must return the premiums). The contract ceases to exist, and the insurer may refuse all past and future claims. If the insurer would have contracted on different terms or for a higher premium (or both) the insurer’s remedies depend upon the type of insurance involved.</core:para>
                        <core:para>Where there is non-life insurance, either side is entitled to terminate future cover on reasonable notice. The consumer is entitled to a refund of the amount of premium relating to the terminated period of the contract. Where a consumer receives notice that the insurer intends to continue the contract on different terms, the consumer can choose either to continue the contract on the amended terms or to terminate the contract, having given reasonable notice. On termination, the consumer is entitled to a refund of the amount of premium relating to the terminated period of the contract.</core:para>
                        <core:para>Where there is a life insurance contract, the insurer has to continue the policy either on the existing terms or on amended terms. If the insurer would have charged a higher premium, if the insurer wishes, it may give the consumer the option to pay the additional premium. It is not, however, obliged to do this. It may prefer to continue the existing premium and pay only a proportion of the claim. The consumer has to be notified of any amended terms and can then choose to continue the contract or to terminate it (with a refund of the outstanding proportion of the premium).</core:para>
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">Part 2</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>This Part concerns variations of contracts. If a qualifying misrepresentation is made before a variation is agreed, the consequences depend upon whether the variation can reasonably be treated separately from the rest of the contract. For example, a consumer takes out annual travel insurance and afterwards, extends the insurance to cover for ski equipment. If the extension to cover ski equipment could be treated separately from the rest of the contract, then the remedies contained in Pt 1 of Sch 1 apply only to the variation. If, however, the variation cannot be treated separately, then the remedies in Pt 1 of Sch 1 apply to the whole of the contract. The misrepresentation arising at the variation stage is treated as if it had been in relation to the whole contract.</core:para>
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">Part 3</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>This is concerned with group insurance and provides that, where there has been a qualifying misrepresentation by one member of a group insurance scheme, the remedies available to the insurer only apply to the cover of that member of the group. It also provides that, where under Pt 1, para 9, there is provision for the consumer to terminate the contract, it is the policyholder who has this right, not the group member who has made the misrepresentation.</core:para>
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">Part 4</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>If there is a contract of marine insurance that is also a consumer insurance contract then, although the Marine Insurance Act 1906, s 84(3)(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>), provides that where an insurer avoids an insurance contract from the outset, the premium is returnable unless there has been fraud or illegality, under Sch 1, para 2, above, the insurer is also allowed to retain premiums in some cases where there are deliberate or reckless misrepresentations.</core:para>
                        <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                        <core:para>For ‘qualifying misrepresentation’, see s 4. For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                     </core:comment>
                  </lnb-leg:heading>
               </lnb-leg:schedule>
               <lnb-leg:schedule edpnum-start="243O">
                  <core:desig value="2">Schedule 2</core:desig>
                  <core:title>Rules for Determining Status of Agents</core:title>
                  <lnb-leg:enabling-legislation>Section 9</lnb-leg:enabling-legislation>
                  <lnb-leg:provision>
                     <core:desig value="1">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">1</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>This Schedule sets out rules for determining, for the purposes of this Act only, whether an agent through whom a consumer insurance contract is effected is acting as the agent of the consumer or of the insurer.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <lnb-leg:provision>
                     <core:desig value="2">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">2</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>The agent is to be taken as the insurer’s agent in each of the following cases—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>when the agent does something in the agent’s capacity as the appointed representative of the insurer for the purposes of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (see section 39 of that Act),</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>when the agent collects information from the consumer, if the insurer had given the agent express authority to do so as the insurer’s agent,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>when the agent enters into the contract as the insurer’s agent, if the insurer had given the agent express authority to do so.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <lnb-leg:provision>
                     <core:desig value="3">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">3</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>In any other case, it is to be presumed that the agent is acting as the consumer’s agent unless, in the light of all the relevant circumstances, it appears that the agent is acting as the insurer’s agent.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>Some factors which may be relevant are set out below.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(3)</core:enum>Examples of factors which may tend to confirm that the agent is acting for the consumer are—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>the agent undertakes to give impartial advice to the consumer,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the agent undertakes to conduct a fair analysis of the market,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>the consumer pays the agent a fee.</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(4)</core:enum>Examples of factors which may tend to show that the agent is acting for the insurer are—</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">a</core:emph>)</core:enum>the agent places insurance of the type in question with only one of the insurers who provide insurance of that type,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">b</core:emph>)</core:enum>the agent is under a contractual obligation which has the effect of restricting the number of insurers with whom the agent places insurance of the type in question,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">c</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurer provides insurance of the type in question through only a small proportion of the agents who deal in that type of insurance,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">d</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurer permits the agent to use the insurer’s name in providing the agent’s services,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">e</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurance in question is marketed under the name of the agent,</lnb-leg:para2>
                     <lnb-leg:para2>
                        <core:enum>(<core:emph typestyle="it">f</core:emph>)</core:enum>the insurer asks the agent to solicit the consumer’s custom.</lnb-leg:para2>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <lnb-leg:provision>
                     <core:desig value="4">
                        <core:emph typestyle="bf">4</core:emph>
                     </core:desig>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(1)</core:enum>If it appears to the Treasury that the list of factors in sub-paragraph (3) or (4) of paragraph 3 has become outdated, the Treasury may by order made by statutory instrument bring the list up to date by amending the sub-paragraph so as to add, omit or alter any factor.</lnb-leg:para1>
                     <lnb-leg:para1>
                        <core:enum>(2)</core:enum>A statutory instrument containing an order under sub-paragraph (1) may not be made unless a draft of the instrument has been laid before and approved by a resolution of each House of Parliament.</lnb-leg:para1>
                  </lnb-leg:provision>
                  <core:comment type="commentary">
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">General</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>This schedule came into force from 6 April 2013 by virtue of the Consumer Insurance (Disclosure and Representations) Act 2012 (Commencement) Order 2013, (SI 2013/450), art 2.</core:para>
                     <core:para>It provides rules to determine for whom an agent is acting where an intermediary assists a consumer in providing a consumer insurance contract.</core:para>
                     <core:generic-hd level="5">Definitions</core:generic-hd>
                     <core:para>For ‘consumer insurance contract’, ‘consumer’, and ‘insurer’, see s 1.</core:para>
                  </core:comment>
               </lnb-leg:schedule>
            </lnb-leg:schedule-grp>
         </lnb-leg:act>
      </lnb-leg:legislation>
   </tr:ch>
</tr:pub-pt>
